Huth, Geoffrey A.; Papers mss137
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
Geof Huth Papers
1960-2006
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
mss137
60.7 cubic ft. 5.65 GB of Electronic Records
The majority of these papers focus on Geof Huth's artistic activities: his creation of artworks, his involvement in the fields of visual and experimental poetry, his productions as a micropublisher, and his work as an active blogger in the worldwide network of online poets. They also document his personal life and professional career in archives and records management.
Biographical Sketch
Geof Huth is an artist and archivist who was born in 1960 in Burlingame, California. He spent the vast majority of his childhood living overseas on four continents and in nine countries. He has lived in California, Virginia, Portugal, Canada, the District of Columbia, Barbados, Bolivia, Ghana, Morocco, Tennessee, Somalia, Germany, and New York. He has also traveled extensively in South America, Europe, Africa, and the United States. He learned to read and write Portuguese and German before he learned English, but he eventually lost the use of both languages. He currently reads, writes, and speaks French and Spanish to some degree.
His first school was the Deutsche Schule zu Porto, the German school of Oporto, Portugal, where the languages of instruction were German and Portuguese. He attended fifteen schools across the world before he graduated from Father Ryan High School in Nashville, Tennessee, in 1978. He graduated with a BA in English from Vanderbilt University in 1982, received an MA in Creative Writing from Syracuse University in 1986, and earned a Master of Library Science from the University at Albany in 1989. He married Nancy Anne Frye in 1984, and they have two children, Erin and Timothy.
Huth began writing short stories, poetry, and commonplace books when he was a child. In college, he began producing other kinds of art, including films, photography, and other visual art. He has been active in the international visual poetry field since 1985, and has produced a wide variety of language-based art since that time, including poetry, visual poetry, fiction, essays, and creative dictionaries. Huth is a well known authority on visual poetry and has spent years writing visual poetry criticism and theory, most of it published to his weblog, dbqp: visualizing poetics.
Starting in 1987, Huth became an active micropublisher, releasing small publications in small editions, first through his micropress dbqp, which publishes language, visual, and conceptual poetry, comics, prose, and other artistic and usually minimalist works. The press publishes a number of different series and magazines, including Alabama Dogshoe Moustache (an irregular poetry journal); Socks, Dregs and Rocking Chairs (an occasional comic book); The Subtle Journal of Raw Coinage (a once-monthly magazine printing undefined invented words from antiquity to the present), and A Voice Without Sides (a limited edition magazine of all types of art, published in exotic ways). Begun in 1989, pdqp, the sister press to dbqp, publishes works primarily related to Huth's family (such as the family's annual holiday cards) and short runs of works by Huth himself (such as programs for his poetry readings). Involved in mailart for years, Huth has released most of his mailart under the qbdp imprint since 2004. He also produces unique bookworks (including diaries, notebooks, and artist's books) under the imprint bqpd.
By 2003, most of Huth's artistic output became focused on the World Wide Web. He began to produce dbqp: visualizing poetics, a daily weblog on the topic of verbo-visual art in general and visual poetry in particular. He also began to produce other weblogs, including one on mailart (qbdp: the mailartworks) and a daily blog of observational prose poems (One Million Footnotes). Many of his works, particularly those digital works that cannot exist on paper, continue to be published on the Web, in e-zines, blogzines, and websites.
Huth has also been active professionally in archives and records management and has served as the executive officer of the Mid-Atlantic Regional Archives Conference, the Lake Ontario Archives Conference (now the New York Archives Conference), Capital Area Archivists of New York, and the Albany Chapter of the Association of Records Managers and Administrators (now referred to simply as ARMA). He has also chaired the Electronic Records and Government Records sections of the Society of American Archivists. Huth regularly speaks on archives and records management, particularly electronic records, across the country. He currently is the Director of Government Records Services at the New York State Archives.
Scope and Contents
The majority of these papers focus on Geof Huth's artistic activities: his creation of artworks, his involvement in the fields of visual and experimental poetry, his productions as a micropublisher, and his work as an active blogger in the worldwide network of online poets. Although Huth began writing poetry and short stories as a child, few of these works survive. His frequent moves during his childhood were opportunities for discarding unnecessary materials such as drafts of writing. Huth's records provide good documentation of the interrelated international fields of visual poetry, experimental poetry, and mailart from the 1980s until the present. Huth's papers include a wide range of media, including broadsides and other large-format paper publications, books, videotapes, audiotapes, electronic media, and super-8 and 16mm films. Huth has created a wide range of artistic and literary works, including very early digital poems written in Apple BASIC and still readable via Apple II emulator software. The bulk of Huth's creative works range from the mid-1980s until the present.
The papers also document Huth's personal life, including his school career, travels, family, and friendships. Through various records, including newspaper clippings, his biographical records provide information about his personal activities as a child and an adult. His correspondence provides sometimes detailed information about his life, art, and relationships, and his weblogs provide much detail about his life and biography.
Finally, these papers document Huth's career in archives and records management. The association records in his biographical files document the archives and records management profession and Geof Huth's role in various associations in New York State and across the country. His work records document his presentations across the country and his various professional positions. These records also include copies of publications and articles written by Huth.
The primary language of these records is English, but other languages present in these papers include Danish, Finnish, French, Georgian, German, Italian, Norwegian, Portuguese, Somali, and Spanish.
Arrangement of the Collection
The collection is organized into 12 series.
Acquisition Information
All initial items in this manuscript group were donated to the University Libraries, M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections and Archives, by Geof Huth in October-December 2006 and January 2007. Geof Huth donated subsequent materials in 2010-2011, 2015, and 2017-2019 and these items have not been added to the finding aid.
Access
Access to this record group is unrestricted.
Schenectady, New York; Literature; Art; Visual poetry; Experimental poetry; Poetry--Electronic publishing; Art--Electronic publishing; Photographs; Correspondence; Notes; Sound recordings; Manuscripts (document genre); Huth, Geof
- Biographical Records, 1960; 1962; 1964-2006; 1; 9 cubic ft.
  Scope and Contents
  This series consists of copies of art and professional vitae, newspaper clippings about Geof Huth and his work, school records, records relating to readings given by and art shows displaying Huth's visual art and visual poetry, and files relating to associations Huth has been active in (including archival associations).
  - Art, 1978; 1981; 1985-2006; 1.1; 3.5 cubic ft.
    Includes documentation of Huth's art activities and non-work writing activities, including files on his art exhibitions and poetry readings. Includes one cubic foot of odd-sized exhibition records, about a cubic foot of rolled acetates from a year 2000 exhibition, and two metal file card cases documenting the submission of his writing to journals.
    Arrangement
    Arranged alphabetically, with exhibitions and readings. Arranged chronologically thereunder.
    - Art, Acceptances, 1985-1987 (Box 1 (1-Biographical Records), Folder 1)
    - Art, Acceptances, 1988 (Box 1 (1-Biographical Records), Folder 2)
    - Art, Acceptances, 1989 (Box 1 (1-Biographical Records), Folder 3)
    - Art, Acceptances, 1990-1992 (Box 1 (1-Biographical Records), Folder 4)
    - Art, Art Resumes, 1991-2006 (Box 1 (1-Biographical Records), Folder 5)
    - Art, Articles about Geof Huth, 1993-2006 (Box 1 (1-Biographical Records), Folder 6)
    - Art, Card File of Writing Submissions, 1987-1993 (Box 1 (1-Biographical Records), Folder 7)
    - Art-Correspondence, Front Street Trolley, 1978 (Box 1 (1-Biographical Records), Folder 8)
    - Art-Correspondence, In a Word, 1990; 1992 (Box 1 (1-Biographical Records), Folder 9)
    - Art-Correspondence, Synergism, 1996 (Box 1 (1-Biographical Records), Folder 10)
    - Art-Correspondence, The Encyclopedia of Local History Contract, 1999-2001 (Box 1 (1-Biographical Records), Folder 11)
    - Art-Correspondence, Dictionary of the Avant-Gardes, 2000 (Box 1 (1-Biographical Records), Folder 12)
    - Art-Correspondence, LIT, 2004 (Box 1 (1-Biographical Records), Folder 13)
    - Art-Exhibitions, Student Art Exhibition, Cohen Art Building, Vanderbilt University, 13 December 1981 (Box 1 (1-Biographical Records), Folder 14)
    - Art-Exhibitions, Pony Express 88, International Mail Art Show, Junior College of Albany, Albany, NY, 22 February-14 March 1988 (Box 1 (1-Biographical Records), Folder 15)
    - Art-Exhibitions, The International Shadow Project, Art Gallery, San Diego State University, Calexico, California, 1989 August-1989 September (Box 1 (1-Biographical Records), Folder 16)
    - Art-Exhibitions, The Last Decade 1980-1990-2000, III International Biennial of Visual/Experimental/Alternative Poetry in Mexico, 1989 October (Box 1 (1-Biographical Records), Folder 17)
    - Art-Exhibitions, Remote Scientific Base Mail Art Traveling Gallery, 1990 (Box 1 (1-Biographical Records), Folder 18)
    - Art-Exhibitions, The International Shadows Project, Woodland Pattern Gallery, Milwaukee, Wisconsin, 17 June-6 August 1990 (Box 1 (1-Biographical Records), Folder 19)
    - Art-Exhibitions, III International Biennial of Visual, Experimental, and Alternative Poetry, 5-14 July 1990 (Box 1 (1-Biographical Records), Folder 20)
    - Art-Exhibitions, Visualog 3: An International Exhibition of Visual Poetry and Language Art, Alternatives, San Luis Obispo, California, 10 October-11 November 1990 (Box 1 (1-Biographical Records), Folder 21)
    - Art-Exhibitions, Visualog IV, 8 April-30 May 1991 (Box 1 (1-Biographical Records), Folder 22)
    - Art-Exhibitions, Jazz Mail Art, 13 July-11 August 1991 (Box 1 (1-Biographical Records), Folder 23)
    - Art-Exhibitions, The Reading Room, 19 July-11 August 1991 (Box 1 (1-Biographical Records), Folder 24)
    - Art-Exhibitions, The Reading Room, William Busta Gallery, Cleveland, Ohio, 19 July-11 August 1991 (Box 1 (1-Biographical Records), Folder 25)
    - Art-Exhibitions, IV Bienial de Poesia Visual/Experimental/Alternitiva, 1992 (Box 1 (1-Biographical Records), Folder 26)
    - Art-Exhibitions, IV Bienial Internacional de Poesia Visual/Experimental, Justina Corbacho, Madrid, Spain, 1992 (Box 1 (1-Biographical Records), Folder 27)
    - Art-Exhibitions, Mail Art Show: Visual Poetry, Tbilisi, Georgia, 1992 (Box 1 (1-Biographical Records), Folder 28)
    - Art-Exhibitions, The Beauty in Breathing, Selections from the Ruth and Marvin Sackner Archive of Concrete and Visual Poetry, American Lung Association/American Thoracic Society International Conference, Miami Beach, Florida, 16-20 May 1992 (Box 1 (1-Biographical Records), Folder 29)
    - Art-Exhibitions, Steckenpferde Internationale Visuelle Poesie, Exhibit Catalog, 1993 (Box 1 (1-Biographical Records), Folder 30)
    - Art-Exhibitions, Mostra Euro-Americana de Poesia Visual, 10-17 August 1996 (Box 1 (1-Biographical Records), Folder 31)
    - Art-Exhibitions, Networking Artists and Poets, Assembling from the Ruth and Marvin Sackner Archive of Concrete and Visual Poetry, University of Pennsylvania Library, Philadelphia, 17 April-27 June 1997 (Box 1 (1-Biographical Records), Folder 32)
    - Art-Exhibitions, The Next Word Text and/as Image and/as Design and/as Meaning Neuberger Museum of Art, Purchase College, 20 September 1998-31 January 1999 (Box 1 (1-Biographical Records), Folder 33)
    - Art-Exhibitions, Wooords, Ayers-Knisely Gallery, The Arts Center of the Capital Districts, Announcements, 2000 October-2001 January (Box 1 (1-Biographical Records), Folder 34)
    - Art-Exhibitions, Woords, Ayers-Knisely Gallery, The Arts Center of the Capital District, Catalog, 2000 October-2001 January (Box 1 (1-Biographical Records), Folder 35)
    - Art-Exhibitions, Woords, Correspondence, 2000 August-2001 January (Box 1 (1-Biographical Records), Folder 36)
    - Art-Exhibitions, Woords, Exhibit Labels, 2000 October-2001 January; 3 folders (Box 1 (1-Biographical Records), Folder 37-39)
    - Art-Exhibitions, Woords, Exhibit Title Label, 2000 October-2001 January (Box 1 (1-Biographical Records), Folder 40)
    - Art-Exhibitions, Woords, Visual Poem Acetates, 2000 October-2001 January (Box 1 (1-Biographical Records), Folder 41)
    - Art-Exhibitions, An American Avant Garde: Second Wave, 2002 (Box 1 (1-Biographical Records), Folder 42)
    - Art-Exhibitions, Family, Alderich Museum of Contemporary Art, Announcements, 2002 (Box 1 (1-Biographical Records), Folder 43)
    - Art-Exhibitions, Family, Art Daze Announcements, 2002 (Box 1 (1-Biographical Records), Folder 44)
    - Art-Exhibitions, Family, Art Guide, 2002 (Box 1 (1-Biographical Records), Folder 45)
    - Art-Exhibitions, Family, Correspondence, 2002 (Box 1 (1-Biographical Records), Folder 46)
    - Art-Exhibitions, Family, Exhibit, Alderich Museum of Contemporary Art, Exhibit Catalog, 2002 (Box 1 (1-Biographical Records), Folder 47)
    - Art-Exhibitions, Family, Familiar Wordex: A Rolodictionary of Family Words, 2002 (Box 1 (1-Biographical Records), Folder 48)
    - Art-Exhibitions, Family, Familiar Words: How We Speak Alone Together, 1996; 2002 (Box 1 (1-Biographical Records), Folder 49)
    - Art-Exhibitions, Family, Press Clippings, 2002 (Box 1 (1-Biographical Records), Folder 50)
    - Art-Exhibitions, The Murphybed Huthache, 107 Neville Hall, University of Maine at Orono, 29 October-3 December 2004 (Box 1 (1-Biographical Records), Folder 51)
    - Art-Exhibitions, I, Foreign Eye, Neopolis, Cleveland, Ohio, 29 October-10 December 2004 (Box 1 (1-Biographical Records), Folder 52)
    - Art-Exhibitions, Rondo Community Library Installation, St. Paul, Minnesota, 2005 (Box 1 (1-Biographical Records), Folder 53)
    - Art-Exhibitions, Visual Poetry (Vispo), Durban Segnini Gallery, Miami, Florida, 2005 March (Box 1 (1-Biographical Records), Folder 54)
    - Art-Exhibitions, Visual Poetry/Poesia Visual, Durban Segnini Gallery, Miami Florida, 2005 March 05-2005 March 26 (Box 1 (1-Biographical Records), Folder 55)
    - Art-Exhibitions, "Your Library" Mail Art Show, 2005 (Box 1 (1-Biographical Records), Folder 56)
    - Art-Exhibitions, Infinity, an exhibition of visual poetry and artworks built on/from/around words and letters, 2005 Spring (Box 1 (1-Biographical Records), Folder 57)
    - Art-Exhibitions, Text Festival, Bury, Lancashire, England, UK, Participated in "Different Alphabets", 19 March-27 November 2005 (Box 1 (1-Biographical Records), Folder 58)
    - Art-Exhibitions, Mostra Internacional de Poesia Visual, 13 June 2005-8 July 2005 (Box 1 (1-Biographical Records), Folder 59)
    - Art-Exhibitions, Sound Vision/ Vision Sound III, 7 July-6 August 2005 (Box 1 (1-Biographical Records), Folder 60)
    - Art-Exhibitions, Sound Vision/ Vision Sound III, An International Exhibition of Verbo-Visual Artwork and Performance, The Nave Gallery, Somerville, Massachusetts, 7 July-6 August 2005 (Box 1 (1-Biographical Records), Folder 61)
    - Art-Exhibitions, Digestions: Mémoire et Transmission, Museé d'Art moderne et d'Art Contemporain, Ville de Liège, Belgium, 2005 September-2005 October (Box 1 (1-Biographical Records), Folder 62)
    - Art-Exhibitions, Blends and Bridges, An International Survey of Contemporary Visual Poetry and Related Art, 1-30 April 2006 (Box 1 (1-Biographical Records), Folder 63)
    - Art-Exhibitions, Visual Poetry, UBU Studio Art Gallery, Portland, Maine, Advertising Poster, 2-30 June 2006 (Box 1 (1-Biographical Records), Folder 64)
    - Art-Exhibitions, Visual Poetry, UBU Studio, Portland, Maine, 2-30 July 2006 (Box 1 (1-Biographical Records), Folder 65)
    - Art-Exhibitions, Visual Poetry, Poster, 2006 (Box 1 (1-Biographical Records), Folder 66)
    - Art-Interviews, Interview by Craig Hill and Ron Silliman at E-X-C-H-A-N-G-E-V-A-L-U-E-S, 13 July 2005 (Box 1 (1-Biographical Records), Folder 67)
    - Art, Newspaper Clippings, 1978-2006 (Box 1 (1-Biographical Records), Folder 68)
    - Art, Newspaper Clippings, 1992-1995 (Box 1 (1-Biographical Records), Folder 69)
    - Art-Readings, State University of New York at Plattsburgh, 1 February 1988 (Box 1 (1-Biographical Records), Folder 70)
    - Art-Readings, Present(ations) of the Future, Sponsored by The Little Magazine, Albany, NY, 19 January 1995 (Box 1 (1-Biographical Records), Folder 71)
    - Art-Readings, Riverfront Arts Fest, 17 June 2001 (Box 1 (1-Biographical Records), Folder 72)
    - Art-Readings, eyear: an indiscriminate series of poems spoken and seen, Gallery 108, 108 Beacon Street, Somerville, Massachusetts, 5 August 2004 (Box 1 (1-Biographical Records), Folder 73)
    - Art-Readings, Words without Walls, University at Albany, Albany, NY, 5 March 2005 (Box 2 (1-Biographical Records), Folder 1)
    - Art-Readings, eye ful tow ers two, Great Valley, New York, Script, 7 September 2006 (Box 2 (1-Biographical Records), Folder 2)
    - Art-Readings, eye ful tow ers two, comments, 7 September 2006 (Box 2 (1-Biographical Records), Folder 3)
    - Art-Readings, eye ful tow ers two, Handouts, 7 September 2006 (Box 2 (1-Biographical Records), Folder 4)
    - Art-Readings, foureff, something like a performance at the Nave Gallery, Somerville, Massachusetts, 16 July 2005 (Box 2 (1-Biographical Records), Folder 5)
    - Art-Readings, Four Tee Five, Jawbone Series, Albany, NY, 23 September 2005 (Box 2 (1-Biographical Records), Folder 6)
    - Art-Readings, Multi-Voice Concert, Bowery Poetry Club, New York, NY, 5 November 2005 (Box 2 (1-Biographical Records), Folder 7)
    - Art-Readings, MIPO Reading Series at Stain Bar, Brooklyn, NY, with Nico Vassilakis and Erica Kaufman, 28 July 2006 (Box 2 (1-Biographical Records), Folder 8)
    - Art, poetry Lesson, First and Second Graders, Zoller School, Schenectady, NY, 14 May 1996 (Box 2 (1-Biographical Records), Folder 9)
    - Art, Returns of Copyright, 1983 (Box 2 (1-Biographical Records), Folder 10)
    - Art, Reviews by Geof Huth, 1989 (Box 2 (1-Biographical Records), Folder 11)
    - Art, Reviews of Geof Huth's Works, 1979; 1987 (Box 2 (1-Biographical Records), Folder 12)
    - Art, Reviews of Geof Huth's Work, 1992-1995 (Box 2 (1-Biographical Records), Folder 13)
    - Art, Submission Records, 1985-1987 (Box 2 (1-Biographical Records), Folder 14)
    - Art, Various Notes, 1980-1987 (Box 2 (1-Biographical Records), Folder 15)
    - Poster board from the Arts Center of the Capital Region, Woords, Ge(of) Huth, Upstairs in the Knisley-Ayers Gallery, 2000 October-2000 November (Box 3 (1-Biographical Records), Item 1)
    - 24 Canvases with different views of the same picture: a plant in a toilet, Undated (Box 3 (1-Biographical Records), Item 2)
    - A Rolodictionary of Family Words, 2002 (Box 3 (1-Biographical Records), Item 3)
    - Rolled Acetates, 2000 Exhibition (Box 3 (1-Biographical Records), Item 4)
    - 2 Metal File Card Cases documenting the Submission of writing to Journals, Undated (Box 3 (1-Biographical Records), Item 5)
  - Associations, 1977-1978; 1988-2006; 1.2; 1 cubic ft.
    Includes documentation of Huth's involvement primarily in professional and academic associations, especially Capital Area Archivists of New York, the Mid-Atlantic Archives Conference, and the Society of American Archivists. Records include minutes of meetings run or attended by Huth, newsletters, and articles by Geof Huth.
    Arranged alphabetically.
    - American Dialect Society, 2000-2003 (Box 1 (1-Biographical Records), Folder 1)
    - ARMA, Correspondence, 1992-1996; 2002 (Box 1 (1-Biographical Records), Folder 2)
    - ARMA, Membership Directories, 1992-1998 (Box 1 (1-Biographical Records), Folder 3)
    - ARMA, Minutes, 1992-1998 (Box 1 (1-Biographical Records), Folder 4)
    - ARMA, Newsletters, 1992-1993; 1995 (Box 1 (1-Biographical Records), Folder 5)
    - ARMA, Region VII, 1995; 1997 (Box 1 (1-Biographical Records), Folder 6)
    - Capital Area Archivists of New York, Incorporation of CAA, 1993-1994 (Box 1 (1-Biographical Records), Folder 7)
    - Capital Area Archivists of New York, Lists of Meetings and Officers, 1982-1993 (Box 1 (1-Biographical Records), Folder 8)
    - Capital Area Archivists of New York, Membership Lists, 1993-1997 (Box 1 (1-Biographical Records), Folder 9)
    - Capital Area Archivists of New York, Joint Meeting with Lake Ontario Archives Conference, 1993 (Box 1 (1-Biographical Records), Folder 10)
    - Capital Area Archivists of New York, Minutes, 1989-1997 (Box 1 (1-Biographical Records), Folder 11)
    - Capital Area Archivists of New York, Newsletters, 1989-2002 (Box 1 (1-Biographical Records), Folder 12)
    - Capital Region Archives Dinner Committee, 1999 (Box 1 (1-Biographical Records), Folder 13)
    - Creative Bull, Junior Achievement Company, 1977-1978 (Box 1 (1-Biographical Records), Folder 14)
    - Dictionary Society of North America, Newsletters, 1992-2001 (Box 1 (1-Biographical Records), Folder 15)
    - Dictionary Society of North America, Membership Directories, 1992-2006 (Box 1 (1-Biographical Records), Folder 16)
    - Guilderland Apple Byters, 1990 (Box 1 (1-Biographical Records), Folder 17)
    - Junior Achievement, 1978 (Box 1 (1-Biographical Records), Folder 18)
    - Lake Ontario Archives Conference, 1992-1998 (Box 1 (1-Biographical Records), Folder 19)
    - Lake Ontario Archives Conference, Chair, 1998 (Box 1 (1-Biographical Records), Folder 20)
    - Mid-Atlantic Regional Archives Conference, 2005-2006 (Box 1 (1-Biographical Records), Folder 21)
    - Mid-Atlantic Regional Archives Conference, Award for Service as Co-Chair, Albany Conference, 2005 (Box 1 (1-Biographical Records), Folder 22)
    - Mid-Atlantic Regional Archives Conference, Award for Service as Co-Chair of the Local Arrangements Committee, Saratoga Springs Conference, 1999 (Box 1 (1-Biographical Records), Folder 23)
    - Mid-Atlantic Regional Archives Conference, Ballots, 2000; 2005 (Box 1 (1-Biographical Records), Folder 24)
    - Mid-Atlantic Regional Archives Conference, Biographical Sketches for Nominations, 2001; 2003; 2005 (Box 1 (1-Biographical Records), Folder 25)
    - Mid-Atlantic Regional Archives Conference, Conference Chair, 2005-2006 (Box 1 (1-Biographical Records), Folder 26)
    - Mid-Atlantic Regional Archives Conference, New York State Caucus Chair eNewsletters, 2001-2004 (Box 1 (1-Biographical Records), Folder 27)